Chris Dorward

Profile



Full Stack JavaScript Developer with over 20 years experience in web development. Over that time I have solved many problems, working fast to produce elegant solutions.

Expert in creating User Interfaces using Open Source JavaScript platforms to replace the need for Flash player to create complex single page front ends for any web App.

Confident dealing with customers, businesses and management to develop, update and create innovative solutions to individual problems.

Remains calm and focused when working under pressure. Adaptable, flexible and open to take on new challenges.

100% Remote

At first through necessity and now through choice, the COVID era has given us the opportunity to work in a new way. I worked remotely for UK clients from Australia from 2020 to 2022 and moving to Malta makes that much easier.

Where 100% remote works well is when both sides are experienced in developing software with proper and rigorous Agile processes using tools like Jira, Git & Slack.

Limited overlap focuses attention on daily standup meetings alongside pre planned conversations. This makes for excellent rates of productivity during the rest of our working day, which is conducted and documented asynchronously.

Skills

Perfect Stack

React, Redux, Material UI, Serverless Node, Cloud NoSQL, PWA, GitHub, Jira

Leadership

Management of remote teams Jira, BitBucket, GitHub, Trello Google Meet/Zoom

Agile SCRUM Master

Fullstack

Full Stack JavaScript ES6 / TypeScript

React/Redux

Node

Progressive Web Apps specific JavaScript eg Service Workers & Push

Notifications

Serverless APIs with Lambda & GCP Functions

GraphQL, Apollo

Vanilla &jQuery

Development tooling with Webpack, Gulp and Grunt

TDD & BDD

- Mocha / Chai / Enzyme/ Jest
- Cucumber e2e testing

Frontend & Design

Hand coded, clean, standards compliant HTML5 with CSS3

Responsive, mobile first design

Material UI, Bootstrap etc

SASS & LESS preprocessors

JSS (JavaScript hosted CSS authoring)

Flexbox, Media queries

Flash, PhotoShop, Dreamweaver, Illustrator & InDesign

Server Side

Node, Express & Koa backends for JSON RESTful API web services PHP Open Source platforms WordPress, Magento, Drupal & Laravel MongoDB & NoSQL Databases

Service Reliability

AWS

Firebase, Google Cloud Platform,

OpenShift & Rackspace

Continuous Integration & Build Automation

Virtualisation with Vagrant & Docker

Implementation of LAMP stack on Rackspace Cloud Servers

Load balancing, backup, replication & synchronisation, Cloud Databases

Linux - Linux skills covering server administration

Apache - Setup, Configuration and maintenance

MySQL - Database administration

Professional Specialities

- → Bridging the gap between design and technical
- → As comfortable talking high level functionality with clients about detailed coding problems with developers
- → Fast, efficient problem solving skills
- → Ability to follow and meet a brief
- → Flexible ability to work closely as part of a team or alone
- → Appreciation of commercial pressure

Work History

Senior Software Engineer, Listingslab

June 2020 - Present

→ I have spent the past 2 years building proprietary software for Listingslab and developing a team of developers and business strategy to hand over the CTO role

Product Lead at Wanngi, Brisbane

June 2020 - Nov 2020

→ Led a development team in the conversion of a legacy Progressive Web App written in Angular to an entirely new React framework using custom Open Source software of my own design

Senior Frontend Developer at Codeworx, Brisbane Sept 2019 - Feb 2020

→ Converting a legacy coffeescript/jQuery Poker application to a modern, React based Progressive Web App

Senior Frontend Developer at Rexlabs, Brisbane

March 2019 - August 2019

→ Facilitating the move from legacy PHP/Knockout tech stack to React/Redux.

React Engineer Developer at Boral, Sydney (contract)

August 2018 - February 2019

- → Laying the foundations of a full e2e, continuous integration testing solution using Cucumber/Gherkin and BDD for a suite of React PWAs.
- → AWS/Amplify GraphQL

Senior Front End Developer at Canon Australia, Sydney (contract) March 2018 - August 2018 → Leading the development of a full Progressive Web App from the ground up. Redux, Persistent Store, SaaS API integration, UX and more.

Frontend Engineer at Aligent Consulting, Adelaide April 2017 - March 2018

- → Working with leading Australian e-commerce businesses to develop their Magento websites.
- → Frontend development of existing themes and designs.
- → Development of new Magento modules with JavaScript ES6 to enhance user experience in areas such as checkout.
- → Commercial grade Mobile Progressive Web Apps in React.

Fullstack Developer at usTwo, Sydney (Contract) January-February 2017

- → Lead developer creating a front end React application for Cancer Council NSW. http://healthylunchbox.com.au.
- → The application connecting to a WordPress driven CMS via the new JSON API.
- → PHP development of custom API endpoints
- → WordPress plugin development
- → React App development using ES6 & webpack & managing workflow with GitFlow.

Front End Software Engineer at Alcidion (Contract)

August 2016 - November 2016

- → Working with a small, very fast paced development team using SCRUM methodology.
- → Using React & Redux to build a front end for a medical application aimed at bed management in hospitals.

Contract JavaScript Developer at Huawei, China (Contract) February 2016 - May 2016

- → Working as part of a small, agile team to produce an Isomorphic JavaScript Project Management App using Node & React JS
- → Experienced working within a Chinese company and localising applications in that language.

Contract JavaScript Developer at The Changing Workplace, London September 2015 - Jan 2016

→ Working as part of a SCRUM development team on a large SAAS software solution for the Facilities Management industry catering to clients such as MicroSoft & General Electric.

→ Developing front end JavaScript applications with large datasets linked to a RESTful JSON API.

Self Employed Web Developer, Listingslab Jul 2007 - July 2015

Ran a small business called Listingslab providing Software Engineering Services and web development to clients all over the world. During this period I have:

- → Became expert in WordPress CMS, creating MultiSite Networks, Plugins and Themes.
- → Created mobile first, responsive themes using HTML5, CSS3 & jQuery
- → Worked in SCRUM style team methodology within a team of remote coders using GitHub

Senior Developer, Velo// - Oct 2010 - Dec 2011

- → WordPress MultiSite and custom module and theme development for multiple clients and partner sites
- → Flash & Server Side Scripting

Lead Product Developer, FMG - Nov 2005 - Dec 2006

- → Created an industry leading magazine publishing application called Ceros using Flash.
- → Created complete working prototype from the ground up, seeing it through till launch
- → API Development and Integration
- → Product has been sold commercially since summer 2006

Senior Systems Developer, IG Index - Oct 2004 - Nov 2005

- → Lead Flash developer in the creative department
- → Migrated IG Index front end systems to a 3rd Generation flash platform as part of a large, London based development team
- → Execution of advertising banners, partner websites and Marketing campaigns.

Systems Developer, Cantor Fitzgerald, London - Sep 2003 - Aug 2004
Senior Flash Developer, Eurobet, London - Apr 2003 - Aug 2003
Flash Developer, Pearson Broadband, London - Sept 2002 - Feb 2003
Senior Web Developer, Kyunet, Sydney - Oct 2001 - Aug 2002
Senior Flash Developer, KPE London - Feb 2000 - Jul 2001
Web Developer, 4MAT, London - May 1999 - Jan 2000
Flash Developer, Aspinalls Online Casino, London - May 1999 - July 1999

Education

Newcastle University UK, Psychology BSc Woodbridge School, Suffolk (1994) A Levels in Maths, Physics & Chemistry 10 GCSE's, all Grade A. Spoken languages: English, German, French

Interests

I spent many years living in Chamonix, France where I became a skier. I've been a scuba diver for 25 years and since moving to Australia have embraced spearfishing and motorbikes. I also write a lot.